Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- United States Attorney for Western Pennsylvania, 1969-1975; VII.
  - United States Attorney of Western Pennsylvania's Files, 6.
    - Hoiles Committee Meeting: Response from U.S. Attorneys to Proposed Amendment to Rule 16 (B) of the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure, 1975 (Box 41, Folder 20)
    - Reactions to H.R. 6799: Federal Rules of Criminal Procedures Amendments Act, 1975 (Box 41, Folder 21)
    - "Representative Examples of Threats to Government Witnesses in Federal Prosecutions 1970-1975" submitted by Thornburgh, Chairman of the Legislation and Court Rules Subcommittee, Attorney General's Advisory Committee of U.S. Attorneys", March 31, 1975 (Box 41, Folder 22)
    - Newspaper clippings and ephemera about Thornburgh's appointment as Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division, 1975 (Box 41, Folder 23)
    - Employment File of Thornburgh, U.S. Attorney, 1969-1975 (Box 41, Folder 24)
    - Thornburgh's United States Attorney ephemera, 1969-1975 (Box 41, Folder 25)
    - Thornburgh's personal daily calendars, 1970-1971 (Box 41, Folder 26)
  - Memoranda, 7.
    Folders here are arranged chronologically, each of which contains several months of memoranda from June 1969 through July 1975. The first section is a miscellaneous group of memoranda from various persons at DOJ, several related to the USA Advisory Committee, and three from Scarlata, a Thornburgh staff attorney. All the remaining and numerous memoranda are an intriguing array sent by Thornburgh to staff members or "to file" and cover a wide range of topics, especially including cases. Since actual case files ultimately were kept by the Office, these memoranda serve as the only internal reference to these notable cases. The memoranda were used generally by Thornburgh to communicate updates and information on criminal activities, criminal cases, investigations, allegations, and procedures to staff and colleagues.
    - Memoranda from DOJ and USA staff attorneys
      - 1970-1975 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda from USA Thornburgh
      - June 5, 1969 - December 31, 1969 (Box 42, Folder 2-3)
      - 1970 (Box 42, Folder 4-7)
      - 1971 (Box 42, Folder 8-11)
      - 1972 (Box 42, Folder 12-14)
      - 1973 (Box 42, Folder 15-17)
      - 1974 (Box 42, Folder 18-20)
      - January-July, 1975 (Box 42, Folder 21-22)
  - Attorney General's United States Attorneys Advisory Committee, 8.
    Folders here are arranged chronologically and include minutes and reports from the Advisory Committee (AGAC) meetings (1974-1975). "For the first time in the [Justice] Department's history, [AG Richardson] established a mechanism for the systematic input of the ninety-three U.S. Attorneys into the Attorney General's office. The AG's Advisory Committee of U.S. Attorneys was made of a dozen representative holders of that office and became, over the years, a valuable sounding board for a succession of Attorney Generals. I was among the first appointed to the Committee" ("Evidence" draft, p. 196).
    Thornburgh's principal contribution was to co-chair a Subcommittee on Field Offices, the final report of which, dated February 15, 1974, is included here. Most of the focus of this inquiry was on the "Strike Forces" operated out of the Organized Crime and Racketeering Section of the Department's Criminal Division (see "Strike Forces Subcommittee" files here). Materials include: memoranda, reports and annotated articles. Topics covered in this subseries may overlap with Thornburgh's subsequent work as the Assistant Attorney General (1975-1977) in charge of the Criminal Division.
    - Minutes
      - The Attorney General's Advisory Committee of United States Attorneys (AGAC) First and Second Reports and Recommendations to the Attorney General, 1974-1975 (Box 42, Folder 23)
      - AGAC Meeting, San Francisco, California, April 24, 1974 - April 26, 1974 (Box 42, Folder 24)
      - AGAC Meeting, Washington, D.C., June 18, 1974 - June 20, 1974 (Box 42, Folder 25)
      - Report of Legislation and Court Rules Subcommittee to the AGAC, September 26, 1974 (Box 42, Folder 26)
      - AGAC Meeting, New Orleans, Louisiana, October 14, 1974 - October 15, 1974 (Box 42, Folder 27)
      - AGAC Meeting, Washington, D.C., January 14, 1975 - January 16, 1975 (Box 42, Folder 28)
      - AGAC Meeting, Washington, D.C., March 18, 1975 - March 19, 1975 (Box 42, Folder 29)
    - Reports and Collected Material
      - AGAC, Subcommittee on Field Offices (strike forces), 1974-1975 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      - "The United States Attorney's Advisory Committee to the Attorney General of the U.S. Report of Subcommittee on Department of Justice Field Office Operations: Concepts and Relationships with U.S. Attorneys", February 15, 1974 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      - AGAC: reports, memoranda, teletypes, annotated articles, 1973-1975 (Box 43, Folder 3-5)
  - Strike Force Subcommittee of the Attorney General's United States Attorneys Advisory Committee, 9.
    These are the files of the Subcommittee on Field Offices, known familiarly as the "strike force" subcommittee. The materials primarily evaluate the effectiveness of strike forces within various U.S. Attorney jurisdictions. These includes memoranda, teletypes, correspondence, news releases, reports, annotated articles and the questionnaire that Thornburgh issued to all of the U.S. Attorneys for evaluation of the Organized Crime Strike Forces in their districts. The final reports of this subcommittee are included with the above "Advisory Committee" files.
    Strike Forces are federal teams comprised of investigators and prosecutors who combine their efforts in a single geographic area with a significant organized crime problem in an attempt to control organized crime and racketeering activities within that area. "The 'Strike Forces' had become institutionalized and expanded under [Attorney General] John Mitchell to the point that considerable friction had developed in a number of areas over 'turf' issues and the allocation of cases between the U.S. Attorney, the presidentially-appointed chief law enforcement officer for the district, and the local 'Strike Force' chief, appointed by and responsible to the Attorney General ... Our report, ultimately recommended that the 'Strike Forces' be returned to their original status as 'trouble-shooting' teams and that the role of the U.S.Attorney as the chief federal law enforcement officer in his community be reaffirmed" ("Evidence" draft, p. 196-7).
    Files of the other subcommittees of the Attorney General's U.S. Attorneys Advisory Committee follow here. Also see "Assistant Attorney General, Criminal Division" files on Strike Forces.
    - President's Advisory Council on Executive Organization: Report on the Effectiveness of the Executive Branch in Combating Organized Crime: Strike Force Section, October 16, 1969 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Strike Force reports, 1969-1976 (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Memoranda Regarding Strike Force/Organized Crime, 1969-1970, 1973-1975 (Box 43, Folder 8-9)
    - Office of the Attorney General: Order no. 431-70 Establishing Guidelines Governing Interrelationships Between Strike Forces and U.S. Attorneys' Offices, April 20, 1970 (Box 43, Folder 10)
    - Questionnaires received from United States Attorneys in areas with a Strike Force (and commentary), 1973 (Box 43, Folder 11-12)
    - Results of U.S. Attorneys' Answers to Strike Force Questionnaire, 1973-1974 (Box 43, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence from Strike Force Head, 1973-1974 (Box 43, Folder 14)
    - Strike Force related correspondence to and from Thornburgh, 1973-1975 (Box 43, Folder 15)
    - Strike Force teletypes to and from Thornburgh, 1973-1975 (Box 43, Folder 16)
    - Thornburgh notes on Strike Force, 1973-1975 (Box 43, Folder 17)
    - Thornburgh's Strike Force Committee working file, 1973-1976 (Box 43, Folder 18)
  - Subcommittees of the Attorney General's United States Attorneys Advisory Committee, 10.
    These files are arranged by five subcommittees of the Attorney General's U.S. Attorneys Advisory Committee: Subcommittee on Legislation and Court Rules (also see USA Thornburgh files), Subcommittee on Allocation of Case Responsibility and Resources, Subcommittee on Communications and Training, Subcommittee on Investigative Agencies, and the Subcommittee on Criminal Justice. Materials here include memoranda, teletypes, correspondence, news releases, reports and speeches with Thornburgh annotations throughout. Files for the Field Offices Subcommittee that reviewed strike forces are in the separate above section.
    - Subcommittee on Legislation and Court Rules, 1973-1974 (Box 44, Folder 1-2)
    - Subcommittee on Allocation of Case Responsibility and Resources, 1973-1974 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Subcommittee on Communications and Training, 1974 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Subcommittee on Investigative Agencies, 1973-1974 (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Subcommittee on Criminal Justice: Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure Amendments Act (H.R. 6799), 1974-1975 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - United States Attorney's Office Cases, 11.
    Folders in this subseries are arranged chronologically and most of the materials are newspaper clippings collected by Thornburgh since the "official" legal case files remain with the U.S. Attorney's Office. It should be noted, however, that there are extremely interesting references to cases in the "Memoranda" section. The cases involve official corruption in Pennsylvania government, organized crime and racketeering. The bulk of the material focuses on the official corruption case involving District Attorney Robert Duggan, chief of Pittsburgh's Racket Squad.
    - Government case News Clippings (annotated), 1969-1975 (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Case articles (annotated), 1969-1975 (Box 44, Folder 8-9)
    - Robert Duggan Case, 1966-1974 (Box 44, Folder 10-11)
    - Robert Duggan Case Clippings (annotated), 1969-1977 (Box 44, Folder 12)
    - Samuel Ferraro Case Clippings (annotated), 1973-1974 (Box 44, Folder 13)
    - Frank Mazzei Case Clippings (annotated), 1975 (Box 44, Folder 14)
    - Frank Hilton Case Clippings (annotated), 1974-1975 (Box 44, Folder 15)
    - Milton Shapp and Gene Coon Case Clippings (annotated), 1975 (Box 44, Folder 16)
    - Anthony Grosso, Frank Bruno and Eugene Coon Case Clippings (annotated), 1973-1975 (Box 44, Folder 17)
  - Issue References, 12.
    The Issue References are grouped by topics as follow: Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs, Other Issues, and Reports. The bulk of the materials in this subseries are newspaper clippings, but files also include magazine articles, news releases and reports. Narcotics and dangerous drugs constitute the largest topic. "Other topics" includes mental health and gun control. "Reports" include both published and unpublished materials on issues related to USA Office.
    - Other Issues
      - Narcotics and dangerous drugs (annotated), 1969-1972 (Box 45, Folder 1)
      - Speech notes, 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - Federal Proposals and Action (annotated), 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder 3)
      - International (annotated), 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder 4)
      - Law Enforcement (annotated), 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder 5)
      - Pennsylvania Agencies and Legislation (annotated), 1969-1975 (Box 45, Folder 6)
      - Rehabilitation and Treatment (annotated), 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder 7)
      - Research (annotated), 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder 8)
      - Narcotics and dangerous drugs: Pittsburgh (annotated), 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder 9)
      - Clippings (annotated), 1969-1975 (Box 45, Folder 10)
      - Articles and News Releases (annotated), 1969-1975 (Box 45, Folder 11)
      - Marijuana (annotated), 1969 (Box 45, Folder 12)
      - Methadone Treatment for Heroin Addiction (annotated), 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder 13)
      - Chatham College Drug Lectures, 1970-1973 (Box 45, Folder 14)
      - Narcotics and dangerous drugs: New York (annotated), 1970 (Box 45, Folder 15)
      - Senate Committee Hearings, Pittsburgh, PA, January 18-19, 1971 (Box 45, Folder 16)
      - Mental Health (annotated), 1973 (Box 45, Folder 17)
      - Gun Control (annotated), 1972-1974 (Box 45, Folder 18)
    - Reports
      - "The Challenge of Crime in a Free Society," by the President's Commission on Law Enforcement and Administration of Justice, February, 1967 (Box 45, Folder 19)
      - "Preliminary Draft of Proposed Rules of Evidence for the United States District Courts and Magistrates," by the Committee on Rules of Practice and Procedure of the Judicial Conference of the United States, March, 1969 (Box 45, Folder 20)
      - "Measures Relating to Organized Crime," Hearings before the Subcommittee on Criminal Laws and Procedures of the Committee on the Judiciary of the U.S. Senate, March, 1969, June, 1969 (Box 45, Folder 21)
      - "Organized Crime Control Acts of 1969 and 1970," Reports of the Committee on the Judiciary of the U.S. Senate, 1969, 1971 (Box 45, Folder 22)
      - "What YOU Should Know About Drugs and Narcotics," by Alton Blakeslee, The Associated Press, 1969 (Box 45, Folder 23)
      - "Toward Reducing Crime in Pennsylvania," report of the Legislative-Executive Task Force on Reorganization (Corrections), September 15, 1970 (Box 45, Folder 24)
      - "Making the Safe Streets Act Work: An Intergovernmental Challenge," by the Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations, September, 1970 (Box 45, Folder 25)
      - "State-Local Relations in the Criminal Justice System," by the Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations, August, 1971 (Box 45, Folder 26)
      - "Analysis of the Allegheny County Criminal Justice System: Present Operations and Alternative Programs," by Jacqueline Cohen, Michel Lettre, and Richard Stafford, Carnegie Mellon University, February, 1972 (Box 45, Folder 27)
      - "A National Strategy to Reduce Crime, National Advisory on Criminal Justice Standards and Goals, January 23, 1973 (Box 46, Folder 1)
      - Working Papers of the National Conference on Criminal Justice, January 23-26, 1973 (Box 46, Folder 2)
      - "Public Exposure of Illegitimate Business," by John L. Obrecht, April, 1973 (Box 46, Folder 3)
      - "Standards relating to the Urban Police Function," by the American Bar Association Project on Standards for Criminal Justice, June, 1973 (Box 46, Folder 4)
      - Criminal Behavior and the Control of Crime: An Economic Perspective," by Timothy H. Hannan, November, 1974 (Box 46, Folder 5)
      - "Deskbook on Organized Crime," by the Chamber of Commerce of the United States, undated (Box 46, Folder 6)
      - "An Enquiry How Far the Punishment of Death is Necessary in Pennsylvania," by William Bradford, Esq., undated (Box 46, Folder 7)
      - "Counsel for the United States: An Empirical Analysis..." by James Eisenstein, 1968 (Box 46, Folder 8)